A Register of the S. V. (Sviatoslav Varlaamovich) Denisov Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
S. V. (Sviatoslav Varlaamovich) Denisov Papers
1900-1966
2008C65
Hoover Institution Archives
30 microfilm reels (4.5 linear feet)
These papers contain the correspondence and writings of Sviatoslav V. Denisov, Major General of the Don Cossack Army and participant in the Don Cossack uprising of 1918. In emigration, Denisov was president of the Cossack Union in the United States, and an active member of various Cossack organizations, especially the All-Cossack Union.
Denisov, S. V. (Sviatoslav Varlaamovich)
Access
The collection is open for research
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives
Alternative Forms of Material Available
Partial collection is available on Microfilm
Location of Originals
In part, Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary, Jordanville, New York
Chronology
1878 September 10 Born, Stanitsa Piatiizbianskaia, Luganskaia oblast', Russia
1896 Graduated, Donskoi kadetskii korpus
1898 Graduated, Mikhailovskoe artilleriiskoe uchilishche
1898-1905 Served, 21st Don Cossack battery
1908 Graduated, Nikolaevskaia akademiia general'nogo shtaba
1914 Adjutant, Ural Cossack division
1915 Colonel
1916-1918 Commanding officer, 11th Don Cossack regiment
1918 Took part in the Don Cossack uprising
1918 Major General and commanding officer of the Don Cossack Army
1919 Emigrated to Constantinople (Istanbul, Turkey)
1921 Author, Zapiski. Grazhdanskaia voina na Iuge Rossii 1918-1920
1922-1923 Lived in Berlin, Germany
1923 Arrived in the United States of America
1923 Elected chair of Cossack Union in the United States
1937 Author, Belyi al'bom
1957 April 19 Died, Stratford, CT
Scope and Content of Collection
These papers contain the correspondence and writings of Sviatoslav V. Denisov, major general in the Don Cossack Army and participant in the Don Cossack uprising of 1918. In emigration, Denisov was chair of the Cossack Union in the United States, and an active member of various Cossack organizations, especially the All-Cossack Union.
The Correspondence file includes extensive correspondence with leading Russian émigré military and social leaders, providing a rich source of information on the activities of Cossack activities in the diaspora.
Denisov's Speeches and writings consist mainly of materials relating to his history of the White Army, Belyi Al'bom, as well as research materials and articles on Cossack history.
The Subject file includes materials on the history of the Don Cossacks, the White Army, as well as Russian émigré organizations. Particularly important are the documents dating from 1917 onwards relating to the Don Cossack Army. Of special significance are the materials relating to the All-Cossack Union in the United States, as well as documents relating to the Don Cossack ataman elections.
Printed matter includes appeals and circulars from the civil war period, 1919-1920, published in territories occupied by the White Army, Soobshcheniia Donskoi Armii (1919), issues of Vol'naia kuban', and Velikaia Rossiia.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Holy Trinity Seminary. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Holy Trinity Seminary Archives as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is appended to this register. Any views, findings, conclusions or recommendations expressed in these materials do not necessarily represent those of the National Endowment for the Humanities.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into seven series: Biographical file, Diary, Correspondence, Speeches and writings, Subject file, Printed matter, and Miscellany
Related Material
Nikolai Vasil'evich Fedorov Papers, Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary
Petr Nikolaevich Donskov Papers, Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary
Petr Nikolaevich Krasnov Papers, Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary
Ivan Alekseevich Poliakov Papers, Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary
Biography
After he arrived in the United States in 1923, Sviatoslav Denisov became a prominent and active figure in the Russian Cossack community, becoming chair of the Cossack Union and a member of various Cossack organizations.
Born in Stanitsa Piatiizbianskaia, Russia, on September 10, 1878,to a traditional Cossack family, he embarked on a military career, graduating from the Donskoi kadetskii korpus in 1896 and the Mikhailovskoe artilleriiskoe uchilishche in 1898. He served in the Twenty-first Don Cossack battery and completed the Nikolaevskaia akademiia general’nogo shtaba in 1908. In 1918, he was a commanding officer in the Don Cossack uprising; that same year he was elevated to the rank of major general and commanding officer of the Don Cossack Army.
Denisov immigrated to Constantinople in 1919 and then to the United States, where (as noted above) he played an important role in the formation of Cossack organizations and charitable associations and was an outspoken activist on issues relating to Cossack life in general. He also published a history of the White Army, entitled Belyi al’bom.
Sviatoslav Varlaamovich Denisov died on April 19, 1957, in Stratford, Connecticut.
Don Cossacks.; Diaries.; Photographs.; Russia--History.; Russians--Far East.; Russians--United States.; Russkii Obshche-Voinskii Soiuz.; World War, 1914-1918.
- Biographical file, 1910-1957 and undated. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Autobiographical sketch, calling cards, certificates, employment documents, family correspondence, financial documents, genealogical file, identification documents, inventory of archives, legal documents, medical records, military records, insurance documents, miscellany, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Autobiographical sketch, 1951 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Calling cards, undated (Folder 1: 2)
  - Certificates
    - Baptismal certificate of Igor' Denisov, 1910 (Folder 1: 3)
    - Life insurance, 1944-1953. (Folder 1: 4)
      Includes related correspondence
    - Membership, 1920-1946 and undated (Folder 1: 5)
  - Employment documents, 1925-1934 and undated (Folder 1: 6)
  - Family correspondence
    - General, 1924-1952 and undated (Folder 1: 7)
    - Butlerov, Boris, 1932-1951 (Folder 1: 8)
    - Denisov, Il'ia Vasil'evich, 1949-1952 and undated (Folder 1: 9)
    - Denisov, Igor' Sviatoslavovich, 1927-1952 and undated (Folder 1: 10)
    - Denisova, Tat'iana, 1945 and undated (Folder 1: 11)
    - Denisova, Zoia, 1920-1924 and undated (Folder 1: 12)
  - Financial documents, 1918-1957 and undated (Folder 1: 13)
  - Genealogical file
    - General – Notes, undated (Folder 1: 14)
    - Family history, undated. (Folder 1: 15)
      Typescript, first page is missing
    - Family tree, undated (Folder 1: 16)
  - Identification documents, 1915-1923 and undated (Folder 1: 17)
  - Inventory of archives, 1932 and undated (Folder 1: 18)
  - Legal documents, 1935-1938 and undated (Folder 1: 19)
  - Medical records, 1910-1924 and undated (Folder 1: 20)
  - Military records, 1913-1931 and undated (Folder 1: 21)
  - Red Cross certificates and documents, 1921-1930 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Russian veteran's association (Soiuz russkikh veteranov/invalidov) certificates, identification and membership documents, 1921-1933 and undated (Folder 2: 2)
  - Veterans Administration insurance documents, 1943-1952 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Miscellany, 1923-1938 and undated (Folder 2: 4)
- Diary, 1919 June 8 to August 12 (Folder 2: 5)
- Correspondence, 1917-1957 and undated.
  Cards and letters, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - General
    - Official letterhead, 191?-192? and undated. (Folder 2: 6)
      Includes various Cossack organizations
    - Record of outgoing correspondence, 1952 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Unidentified
    - General, 1916-1957 and undated (Folder 2: 8)
    - A, 1926-1953 and undated (Folder 2: 9)
    - B-E, 1923-1951 and undated (Folder 2: 10)
    - F-G, 1925-1957 and undated (Folder 2: 11)
    - H-I, 1937-1953 and undated (Folder 2: 12)
    - K, 1921-1952 and undated (Folder 2: 13)
    - M, 1935-1952 and undated (Folder 2: 14)
    - N-O, 1921-1953 and undated (Folder 2: 15)
    - P, 1921-1952 and undated (Folder 2: 16)
    - S, 1921-1953 and undated (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - T, 1937-1950 and undated (Folder 3: 2)
    - V, 1935-1952 (Folder 3: 3)
    - Z, 1951 and undated (Folder 3: 4)
  - Abanshin, Gavriil I., 1950 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Abramov, Fedor Fedorovich, 1929-1954 and undated (Folder 3: 6)
  - Abramov, Petr Fedorovich, 1935-1952 and undated (Folder 3: 7)
  - Adamovich, Boris Aleksandrovich, 1936-1939 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Afonskii, Nikolai Dmitrievich, 1937-1939 and undated (Folder 3: 9)
  - Agoev, Konstantin Konstantinovich, 1933-1946 (Folder 3: 10)
  - Akulinin, Ivan Grigorievich and Tamara Konstantinovna, 1923-1945 and undated (Folder 3: 11)
  - Alaverdy, 1948 (Folder 3: 12)
  - Aleks, An., 1938 (Folder 3: 13)
  - Aleksandrov, A., 1948-1949 (Folder 3: 14)
  - Aleksandrov, Nikolai Nikolaevich, 1950 (Folder 3: 15)
  - Anastasii (Gribanovskii), Metropolitan, 1937-1952 and undated (Folder 3: 16)
  - Andreanov, Ivan P., 1938 and undated (Folder 3: 17)
  - Anosov, Ivan F., 1950-1951 (Folder 3: 18)
  - Antoniuk, Stefan, Reverend, 1947-1952 (Folder 3: 19)
  - Antonov, N., 1921 (Folder 3: 20)
  - Ananasov, N., 1919 (Folder 3: 21)
  - Arabian, Z., 1951 (Folder 3: 22)
  - Arkhangel'skii, Aleksei Petrovich, 1945-1953 and undated (Folder 3: 23)
  - Army and Navy Union, U.S.A., 1939 (Folder 3: 24)
  - Arsenii (Chakhovtsev), Archbishop, 1944 (Folder 3: 25)
  - Artemov, Ivan, 1949-1952 (Folder 3: 26)
  - Artemov, Timofei Mitrofanovich, 1949-1951 and undated (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Arzumanov, T., 1931 (Folder 4: 2)
  - Asmus, V., 1952 (Folder 4: 3)
  - Avalov, Pavel Mikhailovich, 1953 (Folder 4: 4)
  - Azagarov, Georg, 1924 (Folder 4: 5)
  - Azhogin, Vasilii Mikhailovich, 1928-1953 and undated (Folder 4: 6)
  - Babkin, Aleksandr Ivanovich, 1950 (Folder 4: 7)
  - Badrukh, A., 1955 (Folder 4: 8)
  - Baiov, Aleksei Konstantinovich, 1923 (Folder 4: 9)
  - Bakhtiar, Boris, 1931 (Folder 4: 10)
  - Bakuta, Luka T., 1949 (Folder 4: 11)
  - Balabin, E., 1952 (Folder 4: 12)
  - Balakhov, A., 1950 (Folder 4: 13)
  - Balashev, Petr Petrovich, 1939 and undated (Folder 4: 14)
  - Basov, Nikolai Ivanovich, 1949-1953 and undated (Folder 4: 15)
  - Beliaevskaia, Elizaveta, 1923-1951 and undated (Folder 4: 16)
  - Beliaevskii, V., 1951 (Folder 4: 17)
  - Belosel'skii, Sergei Sergeevich, 1946-1953 and undated (Folder 4: 18)
  - Belotsvetov, Andrei Nikolaevich, 1949-1954 (Folder 4: 19)
  - Belousov, Ivan Ivanovich, 1939-1951 and undated (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Bel'deninov, Sergei, 1949-1959 (Folder 5: 2)
  - Bibikova, Vera, undated (Folder 5: 3)
  - Biskupskaia, Mrs., 1950 (Folder 5: 4)
  - Bogomolets, Nikolai Fedorovich, 1939 and undated (Folder 5: 5)
  - Boldyrev, A., 1951 (Folder 5: 6)
  - Boldyrev, Oleg, Reverend, 1949 (Folder 5: 7)
  - Boldyrev, Sergei Vladimirovich, 1953-1957 (Folder 5: 8)
  - Bologov, G. K., 1951-1952 (Folder 5: 9)
  - Bondarenko, A., 1949 and undated (Folder 5: 10)
  - Bondarenko, D., 1918 (Folder 5: 11)
  - Bordzilovskii, A. V., 1949-1951 (Folder 5: 12)
  - Bostrem, Valentina, 1950 (Folder 5: 13)
  - Brazol', Boris, 1923 (Folder 5: 14)
  - Bulavko, Ivan F., 1937-1943 (Folder 5: 15)
  - Bur"ianov, V., 1951 (Folder 5: 16)
  - Burkhinov, N., undated (Folder 5: 17)
  - Bus'ko, Petr, 1949-1951 (Folder 5: 18)
  - Bylinskii, Mikhail, 1951-1953 (Folder 5: 19)
  - Chasovoi, 1935-1950 and undated (Folder 5: 20)
  - Chebysheva, Nina and Lidiia, 1948 and undated (Folder 5: 21)
  - Cherepov, A., 1952 (Folder 5: 22)
  - Cherkasov, Ivan, 1952 (Folder 5: 23)
  - Cherniavin, Ioann, Reverend, 1939-1951 and undated (Folder 5: 24)
  - Chepchikovskii, G., undated (Folder 5: 25)
  - Cheslavskii, Vasilii Vladimirovich, 1939 (Folder 5: 26)
  - Consul General of the Republic of Poland, 1922-1923 (Folder 5: 27)
  - Corson, Adam, Reverend, 1951-1953 (Folder 5: 28)
  - Dakhov, Nikolai, 1959 (Folder 5: 29)
  - Danilov, Nikolai Mikhailovich, 1949-1953 (Folder 5: 30)
  - Danil'chenko, Petr Vasil'evich, 1940 and undated (Folder 5: 31)
  - Darovskaia, Ekaterina Mikhailovich, 1923-1947 and undated (Folder 5: 32)
  - Deissmann, Adolf, 1922 (Folder 5: 33)
  - Deriaba, Petr Alekseevich, 1939 (Folder 5: 34)
  - Diakonov, Petr, Reverend, undated (Folder 5: 35)
  - D'iakon, Aleksei L'vovich, 1930-1935 and undated (Folder 5: 36)
  - Dikovskii, Evgenii Vasil'evich, 1947-1951 and undated (Folder 5: 37)
  - Disabled Russian Veterans' Home Association, 1935-1944 (Folder 5: 38)
  - Dobrynin, V., 1922 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Donskoi atamanskii vestnik, 1951-1957 and undated. (Folder 6: 2)
    General note
    See also Subject file/Don Cossacks/Donskoi atamanskii vestnik
  - Donskoi kadetskii korpus Imperatora Aleksandra III, 1931-1950 and undated (Folder 6: 3)
  - Dmitrievskii, Nikolai Aleksandrovich, 1939 (Folder 6: 4)
  - Dolgopolov, Leonid and Valerian, 1940-1950 and undated (Folder 6: 5)
  - Dolgov, N., 1951 (Folder 6: 6)
  - Donskov, M. B., 1952 (Folder 6: 7)
  - Drobashevskii, V., 1951 (Folder 6: 8)
  - Dronov, Mr., 1952 (Folder 6: 9)
  - Dubishchev, B., 1923 (Folder 6: 10)
  - Dukhanin, N., 1949 (Folder 6: 11)
  - Dulin, F., 1951 (Folder 6: 12)
  - Dushenkevich, Konstantin Evgen'evich, 1951 (Folder 6: 13)
  - Eisimontt, Georgii A., 1949-1950 (Folder 6: 14)
  - Efimov, Avenir Gennad'evich, 1937-1950 (Folder 6: 15)
  - Efremov, A., 1952-1956 (Folder 6: 16)
  - Egorovskii, Aleksandr Anatol'evich, 1936-1939 and undated (Folder 6: 17)
  - Elatontsev, Semen Georgievich, 1950-1952 (Folder 6: 18)
  - Eliseev, Fedor Ivanovich, 1949-1957 and undated (Folder 6: 19)
  - El'shin, Aleksandr Iakovlevich, 1946-1951 and undated (Folder 6: 20)
  - English, Woodruff J., 1948 (Folder 6: 21)
  - Essenskii, Manuil, Reverend, 1951 (Folder 6: 22)
  - Fallenberg, Nikolai Fedorovich, 1944-1947 (Folder 6: 23)
  - Faltsinger, E. I., 1957 (Folder 6: 24)
  - Farafontov, Vladimir P., 1950 (Folder 6: 25)
  - Fatima charities, 1953 (Folder 6: 26)
  - Father Flanagan's Boys Home, Inc., 1934-1952 (Folder 6: 27)
  - Fedorov, Petr Vasil'evich, 1938-1939 (Folder 6: 28)
  - Fedulenko, Valentin Vasil'evich, 1952 (Folder 6: 29)
  - Fekula, Pavel Mikhailovich, 1938-1939 and undated (Folder 6: 30)
  - Feodosii (Samoilovich), Archbishop, undated (Folder 6: 31)
  - Feofil (Pashkovskii), Metropolitan, 1946 (Folder 6: 32)
  - Filippov, Georgii, 1941 (Folder 6: 33)
  - Fischer, Harold H. (Hoover War Library), 1932-1939 and undated. (Box-folder 7: 1)
    Includes materials relating to Denisov's archives
  - Folimonov, N., 1949 (Folder 7: 2)
  - Fond kazach'ei pomoshchi, 1946-1952 and undated (Folder 7: 3)
  - Ganadze, Ilarion Il'ich, undated (Folder 7: 4)
  - Gembeker (Guembecher), Galina, 1947 (Folder 7: 5)
  - George, Aleksandra Stepanovna, 1939-48 (Folder 7: 6)
  - Germogen (Maksimov), Bishop, 1922 (Folder 7: 7)
  - Girburger, Nikolai Iakovlevich, 1949-1951 (Folder 7: 8)
  - Gladin, Viktor Petrovich, 1939 and undated (Folder 7: 9)
  - Golokhvastov, V., 1923 (Folder 7: 10)
  - Golovin, Ivan, 1949 (Folder 7: 11)
  - Golovin, Nikolai Nikolaevich, 1925-1939 and undated (Folder 7: 12)
  - Golubintsev, A., 1953 (Folder 7: 13)
  - Golubov, Mikhail Alekseevich, 1949-1951 (Folder 7: 14)
  - Goncharov, Mr., 1957 (Folder 7: 15)
  - Gordeev, G., 1952 (Folder 7: 16)
  - Govalov, Aleksei, 1950-1954 (Folder 7: 17)
  - Grabbe, Antonii, Hierodeacon, 1950 (Folder 7: 18)
  - Grabbe, Mikhail Nikolaevich, 1936-1939 and undated (Folder 7: 19)
  - Grekov, Aleksei Aleksandrovich, 1937-1951 and undated (Folder 7: 20)
  - Grekov, K., undated (Folder 7: 21)
  - Grekov, Lev, Reverend, 1949-1951 (Folder 7: 22)
  - Grekov, Sviatoslav, 1937-1952 and undated (Folder 7: 23)
  - Grigor'ev, Aleksandr Pavlovich, 1938-1946 and undated (Folder 7: 24)
  - Grigor'eva, K. Mikhailovna, 1949-1952 and undated (Folder 7: 25)
  - Grishkovskii, Nikolai, 1951 (Folder 7: 26)
  - Gul'diev, Petr Danilovich, 1945-1949 (Folder 7: 27)
  - Gusev, Aleksei Efimovich, 1939 and undated (Folder 7: 28)
  - Gusev, Anatolii Mikhailovich, 1949-1950 (Folder 7: 29)
  - Gusev, P., 1938 (Folder 7: 30)
  - Henderson, William Henry, 1941 (Folder 7: 31)
  - Holy Trinity Monastery, 1946-1952 and undated (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Home Missions Council, 1924 (Folder 8: 2)
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1939 and undated (Folder 8: 3)
  - Iakovlev, I., 1950 (Folder 8: 4)
  - Ilovaiskii, Vl., 1950-1952. (Folder 8: 5)
    Includes draft copy of obituary, incomplete, undated
  - Il'iashenko, Fedor, 1951 (Folder 8: 6)
  - Il'in, Mark Dmitrievich, 1945 (Folder 8: 7)
  - Imnadze, Evgenii Semenovich, 1934-1945 and undated (Folder 8: 8)
  - Ioann (Maksimovich), Archbishop, 1949 (Folder 8: 9)
  - Ioann (Shakhovskoi), Archbishop, 1949 and undated (Folder 8: 10)
  - Ionov, Aleksandr Mikhailovich, 1928-1951 and undated (Folder 8: 11)
  - Ipat'ev, Vladimir Nikolaevich, 1949-1950 (Folder 8: 12)
  - Isaev, Georgii Rostislavovich, 1947 (Folder 8: 13)
  - Iudin, Ivan, 1931-1932 (Folder 8: 14)
  - Iunak, Antonii, Reverend, 1951-1952 (Folder 8: 15)
  - Iuzefovich, A. M., 1935 (Folder 8: 16)
  - Izmailov, Nikolai Pavlovich, 1933-1951 and undated (Folder 8: 17)
  - Kaklugin, Feoktist Vsevolodovich, 1950-1951 and undated (Folder 8: 18)
  - Kakurin, Ivan, 1952 (Folder 8: 19)
  - Kalishevskii, General, 1935 (Folder 8: 20)
  - Kandyrina, Nataliia, undated (Folder 8: 21)
  - Kargai, Sergei, Reverend, 1949 (Folder 8: 22)
  - Kartashev, P., undated (Folder 8: 23)
  - Kashchenko, A., 1949 (Folder 8: 24)
  - Kasianov, Iakov, 1952 (Folder 8: 25)
  - Kazanovich, B., 1938-1939 (Folder 8: 26)
  - Kern, F. G., 1949-1950 (Folder 8: 27)
  - Kharlamov, Vsevolod, 1949 (Folder 8: 28)
  - Khodnev, Dmitrii, 1953 (Folder 8: 29)
  - Khokhlachev, Nikolai Alekseevich, 1950-1951 and undated (Folder 8: 30)
  - Khol'mston, A., 1952 and undated (Folder 8: 31)
  - Khrabrov, General, 1934 (Folder 8: 32)
  - Khripunov, Mikhail, 1950 (Folder 8: 33)
  - Khvoshchinskii, Vasilii Vladimirovich, 1939 (Folder 8: 34)
  - Kliupfel', Evgenii Vladislavovich, 1928 (Folder 8: 35)
  - Kodakov, Petr Vasil'evich, 1946 (Folder 8: 36)
  - Kokhanik, Petr, Reverend, 1935-1948 and undated (Folder 8: 37)
  - Kokhengauzen, Mr., 1922 (Folder 8: 38)
  - Kolesnikov, Vladimir S., 1949 (Folder 8: 39)
  - Kolesov, G., 1952 (Folder 8: 40)
  - Kolosovskii, Sergei, 1923 (Folder 8: 41)
  - Kol'tsev, Ivan P., 1948-1949 and undated (Folder 8: 42)
  - Komov, Mr., 1939 (Folder 8: 43)
  - Kononov, Ivan Nikitich, 1948-1949 and undated (Folder 8: 44)
  - Konovalov, Petr Il'ich, 1934-1935 and undated (Folder 8: 45)
  - Korienko, Vasilii Mikhailovich, 1938-1939 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - Korff, K. P., 1937 (Folder 9: 2)
  - Kornilova, Valeriia, 1948 (Folder 9: 3)
  - Korochentsov, Aleksandr Viktorovich, 1945-1951 and undated (Folder 9: 4)
  - Korol'kov, Nikolai, 1952-1953 (Folder 9: 5)
  - Korvin-Krukovskii, Boris Viacheslavovich, 1938 (Folder 9: 6)
  - Kostriukov, Nikolai Fedorovich, 1940-1947 and undated (Folder 9: 7)
  - Kovalev, Ivan Arkad'evich, 1951 (Folder 9: 8)
  - Koval', D., 1951 (Folder 9: 9)
  - Kozlov, A., 1923 (Folder 9: 10)
  - Krasnianskii, N., 1951-1952 (Folder 9: 11)
  - Krasnov, Petr Nikolaevich, 1921-1942 and undated. (Folder 9: 12)
    Includes newspaper clipping
  - Krasnova, Lidiia Fedorovna, 1928-1951 and undated (Folder 9: 13)
  - Krasnova, V., 1949-1952 (Folder 9: 14)
  - Krasnoumov, Aleksandr, Reverend, 1945-1951 (Folder 9: 15)
  - Krivov, Aleksei Sergeevich, 1938-1940 and undated (Folder 9: 16)
  - Krivov, S., 1949-1951 (Folder 9: 17)
  - Krotkov, P., 1939 (Folder 9: 18)
  - Kryzhanovskii, Mikhail, undated (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - Kudinov, Aleksandr Ivanovich, 1950 (Folder 10: 2)
  - Kudramov, Vasilii, Reverend, 1935 (Folder 10: 3)
  - Kudrov, Viacheslav Vladimirovich, 1937-1947 and undated. (Folder 10: 4)
    Includes leaflet entitled Nel'zia molchat'
  - Kunakov, A. I., 1939 (Folder 10: 5)
  - Kuritsyn, I., 1934 (Folder 10: 6)
  - Kusonskii, Pavel Alekseevich, 1937-1939 (Folder 10: 7)
  - Kutyrin, S., 1951 (Folder 10: 8)
  - Kutyrin, Vladimir, 1951 (Folder 10: 9)
  - Kuznetsov, Viktor, undated (Folder 10: 10)
  - Kvitkovskii, V., 1948 (Folder 10: 11)
  - Lampe, Aleksei Aleksandrovich, von, 1937-1939 and undated (Folder 10: 12)
  - Lapiken, N., 1950 (Folder 10: 13)
  - Lashkov, Vladimir Ivanovich, 1949-1952 and undated (Folder 10: 14)
  - Lavrov, A., 1951-1952 and undated (Folder 10: 15)
  - Ledovskii, Nikolai Dmitrievich, 1951 (Folder 10: 16)
  - Leonov, V., 1952 (Folder 10: 17)
  - Leontii (Turkevich), Bishop (later Metropolitan), 1939 and undated (Folder 10: 18)
  - Liakhovich, Vladimir Andreevich, 1925-1929 (Folder 10: 19)
  - Liashenkov, N. D., 1951 (Folder 10: 20)
  - Library of Congress, 1932 (Folder 10: 21)
  - Lindstrom, Siegfried F. (War Department), 1939 (Folder 10: 22)
  - Lisitsyn, I. I., 1929-1945 (Folder 10: 23)
  - Lisovoi, Iakov M., undated (Folder 10: 24)
  - Liubarskaia, A., 1949-1951 and undated (Folder 10: 25)
  - Losev, Ivan Vasil'evich, 1939 (Folder 10: 26)
  - Lozin, Gavriil Mikhailovich, 1952. (Folder 10: 27)
    Includes one print of Lozin
  - Luce, Claire Booth, 1945 (Folder 10: 28)
  - Lukoshin, Mr., 1925 (Folder 10: 29)
  - Lysenkovskii, Vasilii, Reverend, 1935-1939 and undated (Folder 10: 30)
  - Makarov, G., 1957 (Folder 10: 31)
  - Makhin, Ivan Kireevich, 1950-1952 (Folder 10: 32)
  - Malevanova, Avgusta, 1948 (Folder 10: 33)
  - Mamantov, Il'ia, 1950 (Folder 10: 34)
  - Mamontova, Ekaterina Vasil'evna, 1951-1953 (Folder 10: 35)
  - Manakin, Viktor K., 1951-1956 and undated (Folder 10: 36)
  - Mandrovskii, N., 1923-1942 (Folder 10: 37)
  - Manokhin, Vasilii Karpovich, 1923 (Folder 10: 38)
  - Markov, Nikolai Evgen'evich, 1924 and undated. (Folder 10: 39)
    See also Correspondence/Vysshii monarkhicheskii soviet
  - Martynov, Boris Evgen'evich, 1939 (Folder 10: 40)
  - Masov, I., 1945 (Folder 10: 41)
  - Matveeva, Nataliia A., 1937-1950 and undated (Folder 10: 42)
  - Matvienko, 1945-1951 (Folder 10: 43)
  - Maybohm (Meibom), Fedor Fedorovich, 1948-1952 (Folder 10: 44)
  - Mazurenko, Konstantin Ivanovich, 1950-1951 (Box-folder 11: 1)
  - Medem, M., 1947-1949 (Folder 11: 2)
  - Medvedev, Petr Ivanovich, 1933-1934 and undated (Folder 11: 3)
  - Mel'nikov, P. A., 1944-1946 (Folder 11: 4)
  - Merzhanov, Boris, 1951 (Folder 11: 5)
  - Mesniaev, Grigorii Valerianovich, 1951 (Folder 11: 6)
  - Meyer, Elizaveta Aleksandrovna, 1939 (Folder 11: 7)
  - Mikhailikov, Mikhail Sergeevich, 1949-1952 (Folder 11: 8)
  - Mikhailov, T., 1952-1956 (Folder 11: 9)
  - Mikhailovskii, A., 1957 (Folder 11: 10)
  - Miller, Evgenii Karlovich, 1931-1937 (Folder 11: 11)
  - Ministere des affaires etrangeres de France, 1923 (Folder 11: 12)
  - Mironov, Petr Aleksandrovich, 1938 (Folder 11: 13)
  - Mogilevskii, Petr V., 1949-1956 (Folder 11: 14)
  - Morozov, Evgenii, undated (Folder 11: 15)
  - Morozov, Vasilii Ivanovich, 1950 (Folder 11: 16)
  - Motud, Ivan P., 1940 (Folder 11: 17)
  - Mulsenkov, Aleksandr Iakovlevich, 1939 (Folder 11: 18)
  - Museum of Russian Culture, 1950 (Folder 11: 19)
  - Murumets, A., 1951 (Folder 11: 20)
  - Nashe vremia, 1951 (Folder 11: 21)
  - National Alliance of Russian Solidarists, 1951 (Folder 11: 22)
  - Naumenko, Viacheslav Grigor'evich, 1939-1953 (Folder 11: 23)
  - Nefedov, Aleksandr, 1952-1953 (Folder 11: 24)
  - Nemtsov, B., 1949 (Folder 11: 25)
  - Neviadomskii, N. E., 1929 (Folder 11: 26)
  - New York Public Library, 1932-1936 and undated (Folder 11: 27)
  - Nikishin, Georgii, 1950 and undated (Folder 11: 28)
  - Nikolaev, Aleksandr Mikhailovich, 1925-1947 (Folder 11: 29)
  - Nikolaev, Grigorii Kuz'mich, 1951 (Folder 11: 30)
  - Nikon (Rklitskii), Bishop, 1949-1955. (Folder 11: 31)